<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 https://dbkapps.gesis.org/DDI/CDC/OAI-PMH-2-5_v0_4.xsd" version="2.5">
	<docDscr>
		<citation>
			<titlStmt>
				<titl xml:lang="en">DDI study level documentation for study ZA5100 Politbarometer - Overall Cumulation</titl>
			</titlStmt>
			<rspStmt>
				<AuthEnty xml:lang="en" affiliation="GESIS">GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences</AuthEnty>
				<AuthEnty xml:lang="de" affiliation="GESIS">GESIS - Leibniz Institut für Sozialwissenschaften</AuthEnty>
			</rspStmt>
			<prodStmt/>
			<holdings URI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/sdesc2.asp?no=5100&amp;db=e" xml:lang="en"/>
			<holdings URI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/sdesc2.asp?no=5100&amp;db=d" xml:lang="de"/>
		</citation></docDscr>
	<stdyDscr>
		<citation>
			<titlStmt>
				<titl xml:lang="en">Politbarometer - Overall Cumulation</titl>
				<parTitl xml:lang="de">Politbarometer - Gesamtkumulation</parTitl>
				<IDNo agency="GESIS">ZA5100</IDNo>
				<IDNo agency="DataCite">10.4232/1.13299</IDNo>
			</titlStmt>
			<rspStmt>
				<AuthEnty xml:lang="en">Forschungsgruppe Wahlen, Mannheim</AuthEnty>
				<AuthEnty xml:lang="de">Forschungsgruppe Wahlen, Mannheim</AuthEnty>
			</rspStmt>
			<prodStmt/>
			<distStmt>
				<distDate date="2019-05-01" xml:lang="en"/>
				<distDate date="2019-05-01" xml:lang="de"/>
				<distrbtr xml:lang="en" abbr="GESIS" affiliation="GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences" URI="http://www.gesis.org/">GESIS Data Archive for the Social Sciences</distrbtr>
				<distrbtr xml:lang="de" abbr="GESIS" affiliation="GESIS - Leibniz Institut für Sozialwissenschaften" URI="http://www.gesis.org/">GESIS Datenarchiv für Sozialwissenschaften</distrbtr>
			</distStmt>
			<serStmt><serName xml:lang="en" ID="A1"></serName></serStmt>
			<verStmt>
				<version xml:lang="en" date="2019-05-01"/>
			</verStmt>
		</citation>
		<stdyInfo>
			<subject>
				<topcClas xml:lang="en" vocab="ZA Category System" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Categories.htm">
Political Issues</topcClas>
				<topcClas xml:lang="en" vocab="ZA Category System" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Categories.htm">
Political Attitudes and Behavior</topcClas>
				<topcClas xml:lang="en" vocab="ZA Category System" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Categories.htm">
Political Parties, Organizations</topcClas>
				<topcClas xml:lang="en" vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e">Mass political behaviour, attitudes/opinion</topcClas>
				<topcClas xml:lang="en" vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e">Government, political systems and organisation</topcClas>
			</subject>
			<abstract xml:lang="en">
Cumulative data set with all variables from the 1977 to 2016 Politbarometer that were collected more than once.

Variable Overview for the comparable variables of the Politbarometer Total Cumulation:

 &lt;a href=https://dbk.gesis.org/Politbarometer/Variables/ target=_blank&gt;Online Variable Overview &lt;/a&gt;

Topics: Intention to vote and party preference (Sunday question); voting behaviour in the last Bundestag election; eligibility or Non-eligibility of parties; various questions about Bundestag and state elections; sympathy scale for the parties; satisfaction scale for the performance of the federal government and the opposition parties; competent parties for various policy fields; democracy satisfaction; correct politicians in leading positions; political interest; self-assessment on a left-right continuum; assessment of the economic situation in the Federal Republic and presumed further development; own economic situation and expected further development; competence of the government or the opposition to various policy fields; most important politicians; scalometers of political personalities; government coalitions; role of various parties in government coalitions; questions on the reunification of the two German states; questions on foreign policy and international relations; questions on European cooperation and the financial crisis; questions on a wide range of domestic policy issues, such as fear of crime, counter-terrorism, data protection or right-wing extremists; questions on social policy, such as pension security, health care, social security systems or birth rate in Germany; questions on economic policy, such as collective bargaining, minimum wage, working hours or tax issues; questions on education policy; questions on defence and disarmament, such as attitudes towards an increased assumption of global political responsibility by the united Germany, deployment of the Bundeswehr or arms trade; questions on environmental protection, energy policy and technical development; ethical and religious questions, such as the evaluation of different views on abortion; questions on migration and policy on foreigners, such as assessment of the proportion of foreigners, attitude to asylum law in Germany, reception and integration of refugees; satisfaction with the state of society; comparison of society with other Western European countries; perceived military threat; peace security; annual review of political events; personal annual outlook; questions on various areas of life, such as holidays, sports or television.

Demography: denomination; church attendance frequency; gender; age; marital status; cohabitation with a partner; children in the household; school education; completed vocational training; university degree; educational aspiration level; occupation; occupational group; household size; head of household; job security; party affiliation; party identification; trade union member in the household; federal state; city size.
</abstract>
			<abstract xml:lang="de">
Kumulierter Datensatz mit allen Variablen aus den Politbarometern der Jahre 1977 bis 2016, die mehr als einmal erhoben wurden.

Variable Overview für die vergleichbaren Variablen der Politbarometer Gesamtkumulation:

 &lt;a href=https://dbk.gesis.org/Politbarometer/Variables/ target=_blank&gt;Online Variable Overview &lt;/a&gt;

Themen: Wahlbeteiligungsabsicht und Parteipräferenz (Sonntagsfrage); Wahlverhalten bei der letzten Bundestagswahl; Wählbarkeit bzw. Nichtwählbarkeit von Parteien; verschieden Fragen rund um Bundestags- und Landtagswahlen; Sympathie-Skalometer für die Parteien; Zufriedenheits-Skalometer für die Leistungen der Bundesregierung und der Oppositionsparteien; Kompetente Parteien für verschiedene Politikfelder; Demokratiezufriedenheit; richtige Politiker in den führenden Positionen; Politikinteresse des Befragten; Selbsteinschätzung auf einem Links-Rechts-Kontinuum; Beurteilung der wirtschaftlichen Lage in der Bundesrepublik und vermutete weitere Entwicklung; eigene wirtschaftliche Situation und erwartete weitere Entwicklung; Kompetenz der Regierung oder der Opposition zu verschiedenen Politikfeldern; wichtigste Politiker und Politikerinnen; Skalometer politischer Persönlichkeiten; Regierungskoalitionen; Rolle verschiedener Parteien in Regierungskoalitionen; Fragen zur Wiedervereinigung der beiden deutschen Staaten; Fragen zur Außenpolitik und internationalen Beziehungen;  Fragen zur europäischen Zusammenarbeit und zur Finanzkrise; Fragen zu vielfältigen innenpolitischen Themen, wie Kriminalitätsfurcht, Terrorabwehr, Datenschutz oder Rechtsradikale; Fragen zur Sozialpolitik, wie Rentensicherung, Gesundheitswesen, soziale Sicherungssysteme oder Geburtsrate in Deutschland; Fragen zur Wirtschaftspolitik, wie Tarifverhandlungen, Mindestlohn, Arbeitszeit oder Steuerfragen; Fragen zur Bildungspolitik; Fragen zu Verteidigung und Abrüstung, wie etwa Einstellung zu einer vermehrten Übernahme weltpolitischer Verantwortung durch das vereinte Deutschland, Einsatz der Bundeswehr oder Waffenhandel; Fragen zu Umweltschutz, Energiepolitik und technischer Entwicklung; Ethische und religiöse Fragen, wie die Bewertung verschiedener Auffassungen zum Thema Abtreibung; Fragen zu Migration und Ausländerpolitik, wie Beurteilung des Ausländeranteils, Einstellung zum Asylrecht in Deutschland, Aufnahme und Integration von Flüchtlingen; Zufriedenheit mit dem Zustand der Gesellschaft; Vergleich der Gesellschaft mit anderen westeuropäischen Ländern; empfundene militärische Bedrohung; Friedenssicherheit; Jahresrückblick auf das politische Geschehen; persönlicher Jahresausblick; Fragen zu verschiedensten Bereichen des Lebens, wie Urlaub, Sport oder Fernsehen.

Demographie: Konfession; Kirchgangshäufigkeit; Geschlecht; Alter; Familienstand; Zusammenleben mit einem Partner; Kinder im Haushalt; Schulbildung; abgeschlossene Berufsausbildung; Hochschulabschluss; Bildungsaspirationsniveau; Berufstätigkeit; Berufsgruppe; Haushaltsgröße; Haushaltsvorstand; eigene Arbeitsplatzgefährdung; Parteineigung; Parteiidentifikation; Gewerkschaftsmitglied im Haushalt; Bundesland; Ortsgröße.
</abstract>
			<sumDscr>
				<nation xml:lang="en" abbr="DE">Germany</nation>
				<nation xml:lang="de" abbr="DE">Deutschland</nation>
				<anlyUnit/>
				<universe clusion="B2" xml:lang="en"/>
				<collDate date="1977" event="start"/>
				<collDate date="2017" event="end"/>
			</sumDscr>
		</stdyInfo>
		<method>
			<dataColl>
				<timeMeth/>
				<dataCollector/>
				<sampProc xml:lang="en">Probability Sample: Multistage Sample

The results are representative of the total electorate in the study area. According to the Elections research group, this is ensured by a strict random selection of the persons to be interviewed. Since August 1988, a two-stage random sample according to the RLD method (Randomize Last Digit) has been used for the sample: First private households are selected, then one person from each household. The person who had the last birthday of the eligible voters in the household is interviewed. The selection basis also includes households that are not listed in the telephone directory and can in principle be reached by telephone via a landline number. The basis is the private numbers entered in the telephone directory, where the last three digits are deleted and then filled with the numbers ´000´ to ´999´ . This database is critically reviewed and adjusted accordingly by consulting the information provided by the Federal Network Agency on the (partial) allocation of number blocks and the directory.

From 1977 to June 1988, a multi-stage stratified random sample according to the ADM master sample was carried out.	</sampProc>
				<sampProc xml:lang="de">Wahrscheinlichkeitsauswahl: Mehrstufige Zufallsauswahl

Die Ergebnisse sind repräsentativ für die Gesamtheit der wahlberechtigten Bevölkerung im Untersuchungsgebiet. Dies wird nach Angaben der Forschungsgruppe Wahlen durch eine strenge Zufallsauswahl bei der Bestimmung der zu befragenden Personen gewährleistet. Für die Stichprobe wird seit August 1988 eine zweistufige Zufallsauswahl nach dem RLD-Verfahren (Randomize Last Digit) verwendet: Zunächst werden Privathaushalte ausgewählt, dann eine Person eines jeden Haushalts. Hierbei wird diejenige Person befragt, die von den Wahlberechtigten im Haushalt als letzte Geburtstag hatte. Die Auswahlgrundlage umfasst auch nicht im Telefonbuch eingetragene Haushalte, die prinzipiell über eine Festnetznummer telefonisch erreichbar sind. Basis sind die im Telefonbuch eingetragenen Privatnummern, bei denen die letzten drei Ziffern gelöscht und anschließend mit den Zahlen ´000´ bis ´999´ aufgefüllt werden. Dieser Datenbestand wird durch Hinzuziehung der Informationen der Bundesnetzagentur über die (Teil-)Belegung von Rufnummernblöcken und des Branchenverzeichnisses kritisch geprüft und entsprechend bereinigt.

Von 1977 bis Juni 1988 erfolgte eine mehrstufig geschichtete Zufallsauswahl nach ADM-Mastersample.	</sampProc>
				<deviat/>
				<collMode/>
				<sources/>
				<weight/>
				<cleanOps>C3</cleanOps>
			</dataColl>
		</method>
		<dataAccs>
			<useStmt>
				<restrctn xml:lang="en">A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</restrctn>
				<restrctn xml:lang="de">A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</restrctn>
				<conditions xml:lang="en"/>
				<specPerm xml:lang="en"/>
			</useStmt>
			<setAvail>
				<avlStatus xml:lang="en"/>
			</setAvail>
		</dataAccs>
		<othrStdyMat/>
	</stdyDscr>
	<fileDscr>
		<fileTxt xml:lang="en"/>
	</fileDscr>
</codeBook>