<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="2.5" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 https://dbkapps.gesis.org/DDI/CDC/OAI-PMH-2-5_v0_4.xsd">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl xml:lang="en">DDI study level documentation for study ZA2800 ALLBUS/GGSS 1996 (Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der  Sozialwissenschaften/German General Social  Survey 1996) </titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="GESIS" xml:lang="en">GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="GESIS" xml:lang="de">GESIS - Leibniz Institut für Sozialwissenschaften</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt/>
      <holdings URI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/sdesc2.asp?no=2800&amp;db=e" xml:lang="en"/>
      <holdings URI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/sdesc2.asp?no=2800&amp;db=d" xml:lang="de"/>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl xml:lang="en">ALLBUS/GGSS 1996 (Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der  Sozialwissenschaften/German General Social  Survey 1996) </titl>
        <parTitl xml:lang="de">Allgemeine Bevölkerungsumfrage der Sozialwissenschaften ALLBUS 1996 </parTitl>
        <IDNo agency="GESIS">ZA2800</IDNo>
        <IDNo agency="DataCite">10.4232/1.11888</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Frankfurt" xml:lang="en">Allerbeck, Klaus R.</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Frankfurt" xml:lang="de">Allerbeck, Klaus R.</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität München" xml:lang="en">Allmendinger, Jutta</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität München" xml:lang="de">Allmendinger, Jutta</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Potsdam" xml:lang="en">Bürklin, Wilhelm</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Potsdam" xml:lang="de">Bürklin, Wilhelm</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Wien" xml:lang="en">Kiefer, Marie-Luise</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Wien" xml:lang="de">Kiefer, Marie-Luise</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Mannheim" xml:lang="en">Müller, Walter</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Mannheim" xml:lang="de">Müller, Walter</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Leipzig" xml:lang="en">Opp, Karl-Dieter</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Leipzig" xml:lang="de">Opp, Karl-Dieter</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Köln " xml:lang="en">Scheuch, Erwin K.</AuthEnty>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="Universität Köln " xml:lang="de">Scheuch, Erwin K.</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt/>
      <distStmt>
        <distDate date="2014-04-14" xml:lang="en"/>
        <distDate date="2014-04-14" xml:lang="de"/>
        <distrbtr URI="http://www.gesis.org/" abbr="GESIS" affiliation="GESIS - Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences" xml:lang="en">GESIS Data Archive for the Social Sciences</distrbtr>
        <distrbtr URI="http://www.gesis.org/" abbr="GESIS" affiliation="GESIS - Leibniz Institut für Sozialwissenschaften" xml:lang="de">GESIS Datenarchiv für Sozialwissenschaften</distrbtr>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName ID="A1" xml:lang="en"/>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2014-04-14" xml:lang="en"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="ZA Category System" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Categories.htm" xml:lang="en">
Society, Culture</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Migration</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Cultural and national identity</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Social conditions and indicators</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Social behaviour and attitudes</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Law, crime and legal systems</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Mass political behaviour, attitudes/opinion</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Government, political systems and organisation</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Social stratification and groupings</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://dbk.gesis.org/dbksearch/Topics.asp?db=e" xml:lang="en">Economic policy</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <abstract xml:lang="en">
Social monitoring of trends in attitudes, behavior, and societal change
in the Federal Republic of Germany.

The main topics in 1996 are: 
1.) Attitudes towards ethnic groups in
Germany and to migration 
2.) Citizenship and country of origin 
3.)Attitudes towards marriage, family, and partnership 
4.) Other topics
5.) ALLBUS-Demography 
6.) Data on the interview (paradata) 
7.) Role of government III (ISSP 1996) 
8.) Added value

Topics: 

1.) Attitudes towards ethnic groups in Germany and to
migration: perceived consequences of presence of foreigners in Germany;
attitude towards the influx of eastern European ethnic Germans, asylum
seekers, labor from EC or non-EC countries; ranking in terms of
importance of different citizenship requirements; perception and
evaluation of discriminatory behavior towards foreigners; opinion on
dual citizenship and on equality under the law for foreigners;
indicators for social distance to ethnic minorities and foreigners;
perceived differences in lifestyle; items on anti-Semitism; support for
the teaching of Islam in public schools; estimation of proportion of
foreigners in East and West Germany; percentage of foreigners in local
county (Kreis).

2.) Nationality and country of origin: first, second, and third
citizenship of respondent and spouse or partner; original citizenship
of respondent and of spouse or partner; country of origin of respondent
and of respondent´s parents and grandparents; length of stay in
Germany.

3.) Attitudes towards marriage, family, and partnership: family as a
prerequisite for happiness; marriage in case of steady partnership;
attitudes towards the role of women in the family; relative importance
of selected educational goals for a child.

4.) Other topics: attitudes towards abortion; general trust in fellow
men and politicians; social pessimism and orientation towards the
future (anomia); reasons for being proud to be a German;
authoritarianism; self-assessment of social class; fair share in the
standard of living; political interest; questions on postmaterialism
(importance of law and order, fighting rising prices, free expression
of opinions, and influence on governmental decisions); self-placement
on a left-right continuum; assessment of economic situations; recall of
past vote in federal elections; reasons for non-voting; fear of
unemployment or loss of business.

5.) ALLBUS-Demography: Details about the respondent: gender; month and
year of birth, age; geographical origin and citizenship; place of
residence (federal state, administrative region, size of municipality,
BIK-type of municipality) and length of residence; religious
denomination, frequency of church attendance; voting intention
(Sonntagsfrage); vote in last election; general education, vocational
training; employment status; details about current occupation,
affiliation to public service, supervisory functions; length of
unemployment; date of termination of full- or part-time employment;
details about former occupation; respondent´s income; marital status.
Details about respondent´s current spouse: general education,
vocational training; employment status; details about current
occupation; current and former citizenships. Details about respondent´s
steady extra-marital partner: common household; month and year of
birth, age; geographical origin and citizenship; general education,
vocational training; employment status; details about current
occupation. Details about respondent´s parents: parent´s and
grandparent´s country of origin; general education of father and
mother; father´s occupation. Composition of household: size of
household; household income; type of dwelling; telephone. Details about
household members: relation to respondent; gender; month and year of
birth, age; marital status. Respondent´s current memberships (Deutscher
Gewerkschaftsbund (DGB, blue-collar union), Deutsche
Angestelltengewerkschaft (DAG, white-collar union), other trade union,
political party).

6.) Data on the interview (paradata): date of interview; time and length of
interview; presence of other people during the interview; respondent´s
willingness to answer questions; evaluation of reliability of
respondent answers; gender, age, and general education of the
interviewer.

7.) Role of government III (ISSP): attitudes towards the observance of
laws; attitudes towards different forms of protest against the
government; willingness to participate and actual participation in
public protest activities or demonstrations against the government;
opinions on freedom of speech for extremists; attitude towards a
miscarriage of justice; perceived threats in the private life through
governmental data collections and computer networks; assessment of
social responsibility of the state in relation to job creation and just
distribution of incomes; attitudes towards economically oriented
government measures; attitudes towards an increase of expenditures of
the government for environmental protection, health service, police,
the educational system, defense, pensions, unemployment benefit,
culture; assessment of the power of the trade unions, private
enterprise and the state; assessment of state responsibility for
socio-political tasks (social support for the elderly, students,
housing provision, job creation; economic growth through assistance to
industry, price stability, etc.); political interest; overall attitude
towards politics and the political system (subjective assessment of
political influence (political efficacy), level of political awareness,
politicians and election promises); lower taxes vs. more extensive
social services; assessment of fairness of tax levels for different
income groups; attitudes towards privatization or nationalization of
selected public institutions; preferences for enactment of
environmental regulations by the Federal parliament or the EU.

8.) Added value: Inglehart-index; family typology, classification
of private households (according to Porst and Funk); International
Standard Classification of Occupations (ISCO 1968, 1988); class
position (according to Goldthorpe); occupational prestige (according to
Treiman); magnitude prestige (according to Wegener); occupational
meta-classification (according to Terwey); weights. 
</abstract>
      <abstract xml:lang="de">
Trenderhebung zur gesellschaftlichen Dauerbeobachtung von
Einstellungen, Verhalten und sozialem Wandel in Deutschland.
Die Schwerpunkte dieser Untersuchung sind für 1996:

1. Einstellungen zu ethnischen Gruppen in Deutschland und zur
Immigration

2. Staatsbürgerschaften und Herkunftsland

3. Einstellungen zu Familie, Ehe und Partnerschaft

4. Sonstiges

5. ALLBUS-Demographie

6. Daten zum Interview (Paradaten)

7. Rolle der Regierung III (ISSP 1996)

8. Ergänzungen und abgeleitete Variablen

Themen: 

1. Einstellungen zu ethnischen Gruppen in Deutschland und zur
Immigration: Wahrgenommene Konsequenzen der Anwesenheit von Ausländern
in Deutschland; Einstellungen zum Zuzug verschiedener Zuwanderergruppen;
Wichtigkeitseinstufung verschiedener Einbürgerungsvoraussetzungen;
Wahrnehmung und Bewertung von diskriminierendem Verhalten gegenüber
Ausländern; Einstellung zur doppelten Staatsbürgerschaft und zur
Rechtsgleichstellung von Ausländern; Indikatoren für soziale Distanz zu
ethnischen Minderheiten und Ausländern; perzipierte
Lebensstildifferenzen; Items zum Antisemitismus; Befürwortung von
Islamunterricht an Schulen; Ausländeranteilsschätzung für Ost- und
Westdeutschland; prozentualer Ausländeranteil auf Kreisebene.

2. Staatsbürgerschaften und Herkunftsland: Erste, zweite und dritte
Staatsbürgerschaft des Befragten und des Ehe- oder Lebenspartners;
Anzahl der Staatsbürgerschaften des Befragten und des Ehe- oder
Lebenspartners; ursprüngliche Staatsbürgerschaft des Befragten und des
Ehe- oder Lebenspartners; Herkunftsland des Befragten und der Eltern und
Großeltern des Befragten; bisherige Aufenthaltsdauer von eingewanderten
Personen in Deutschland.

3. Einstellungen zu Familie, Ehe und Partnerschaft: Familie als
Voraussetzung für Glück; Einstellung zur Heirat bei dauerndem
Zusammenleben der Partner; Einstellung zur Rolle der Frau in der
Familie; Einstufung der Wichtigkeit ausgewählter Lernziele für ein Kind.

4. Sonstiges: Einstellungen zum Schwangerschaftsabbruch; allgemeines
Vertrauen zu Mitmenschen und zu Politikern; sozialer Pessimismus und
Zukunftsorientierung (Anomia); Gründe, als Deutscher stolz sein zu
können; Nationalstolz; Autoritarismus; Selbsteinschätzung der sozialen
Schichtzugehörigkeit; gerechter Anteil am Lebensstandard; politisches
Interesse; Postmaterialismus (Wichtigkeit von Ruhe und Ordnung, von
Bürgereinfluss, von Inflationsbekämpfung und von freier
Meinungsäußerung); Selbsteinstufung auf einem Links-Rechts-Kontinuum;
Einschätzung von Wirtschaftslagen; Wahlrückerinnerung; Grund für
Wahlenthaltung; Furcht vor Verlust des Arbeitsplatzes bzw. der
betrieblichen Existenz.

5. ALLBUS-Demographie: Angaben zur befragten Person: Geschlecht;
Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter; Herkunft und Staatsangehörigkeit;
Wohnort (Bundesland, Regierungsbezirk, politische Gemeindegröße, BIK-
Stadtregion) und Wohndauer; Konfession, Kirchgangshäufigkeit;
Wahlabsicht (Sonntagsfrage) und Wahlrückerinnerung; allgemeiner
Schulabschluss, berufliche Ausbildung; Erwerbsstatus; Angaben zum
gegenwärtigen Beruf, Zugehörigkeit zum öffentlichen Dienst, berufliche
Aufsichtsfunktion; Dauer von Arbeitslosigkeit; Angaben zum ehemaligen
Beruf; Zeitpunkt der Aufgabe hauptberuflicher Erwerbstätigkeit;
Befragteneinkommen; Familienstand.

Angaben zum gegenwärtigen Ehepartner: allgemeiner Schulabschluss,
berufliche Ausbildung; Erwerbsstatus; Angaben zum gegenwärtigen Beruf;
frühere und gegenwärtige Staatsbürgerschaft.

Angaben zum nichtehelichen Lebenspartner: Gemeinsamer Haushalt mit
Lebenspartner; Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter des Partners; Herkunft
und Staatsbürgerschaft; allgemeiner Schulabschluss, berufliche
Ausbildung; Erwerbsstatus; Angaben zum gegenwärtigen Beruf.

Angaben zu den Eltern des Befragten: Herkunftsland der Eltern und der
Großeltern; allgemeiner Schulabschluss von Mutter und Vater; Angaben zum
Beruf des Vaters.

Haushaltsbeschreibung: Haushaltsgröße; Haushaltseinkommen; Wohnungstyp;
Telefonanschluß.

Angaben zu den einzelnen Haushaltspersonen (Haushaltsliste):
Verwandtschaft der Haushaltspersonen zum Befragten; Geschlecht der
Personen; ihr Geburtsmonat, Geburtsjahr, Alter; Familienstand.

Gegenwärtige Mitgliedschaften des Befragten (Deutscher
Gewerkschaftsbund (DGB), Deutsche
Angestelltengewerkschaft (DAG), andere Gewerkschaft, politische Partei).

6. Daten zum Interview (Paradaten): Interviewdatum, Interviewzeitpunkt und
Interviewdauer; Anwesenheit anderer Personen beim Interview;
Antwortbereitschaft des Befragten; Interviewereinschätzung zur
Zuverlässigkeit der Angaben des Befragten; Geschlecht, Alter und
Schulabschluss des Interviewers.

7. Rolle der Regierung III (ISSP 1996): Einstellung zur Befolgung von
Gesetzen; Einstellungen zu verschiedenen Protestformen gegen die
Regierung; Teilnahmebereitschaft und tatsächliche Teilnahme an
öffentlichen Protestveranstaltungen oder Demonstrationen gegen die
Regierung; Ansichten bezüglich der Meinungsfreiheit für Extremisten;
Einstellung zu einem Justizirrtum; empfundene Bedrohung der Privatsphäre
durch staatliche Datensammlungen und Computer-Vernetzungen
(Datenschutz); Einkommensangleichung als Staatsaufgabe und Haltung zu
wirtschaftsbezogenen Maßnahmen der Regierung; Einstellung zur Erhöhung
von Regierungsausgaben für Umweltschutz, Gesundheitswesen, Polizei,
Bildungswesen, Verteidigung, Renten, Arbeitslosenunterstützung, Kultur;
Einschätzung der Macht von Gewerkschaften, Wirtschaft und Staat;
Einschätzung der staatlichen Verantwortlichkeit für sozialpolitische
Aufgaben (Absicherung von alten Menschen, Studenten, Wohnungsversorgung,
Arbeitsplätzen, Wirtschaftswachstum durch Hilfen an die Industrie,
Preisstabilität etc.); politisches Interesse; generelle Einstellungen
zur Politik und zum politischen System (subjektive Einschätzung der
politischen Einflussmöglichkeiten (efficacy), politische Informiertheit,
Politiker und Wahlversprechen); Steuersenkung versus
Sozialleistungsausbau; Einschätzung der Steuergerechtigkeit bei
verschiedenen Einkommensgruppen; Einstellung zur Privatisierung oder
Verstaatlichung ausgewählter öffentlicher Einrichtungen; Präferenz für
Erlass von Umweltgesetzen durch den deutschen Bundestag oder die EU.

8. Ergänzungen und abgeleitete Variablen: Postmaterialismus-Index (nach Inglehart);
Familientypologie, Haushaltsklassifikationen (nach Porst und Funk);
Berufsvercodung gemäß ISCO (International Standard Classification of
Occupations) 1968 und 1988; Klassenlage (nach Goldthorpe);
Berufsprestige (nach Treiman); Magnitudeprestige (nach Wegener);
Einordnungsberufe (nach Terwey); Ost-West-Gewicht für gesamtdeutsche
Auswertungen.

</abstract>
      <sumDscr>
        <nation abbr="DE" xml:lang="en">Germany</nation>
        <nation abbr="DE" xml:lang="de">Deutschland</nation>
        <anlyUnit/>
        <universe clusion="B2" xml:lang="en"/>
        <collDate date="1996-03" event="start"/>
        <collDate date="1996-06" event="end"/>
      </sumDscr>
    </stdyInfo>
    <method>
      <dataColl>
        <timeMeth/>
        <dataCollector/>
        <sampProc xml:lang="en">Sample of individuals: Two stage disproportionate random sample in
western Germany (incl. West Berlin) and eastern Germany (incl. East
Berlin). 
In the first sampling stage, 104 municipalities (Gemeinde) were selected in West Germany and 47 in East Germany with a probability proportional to their total
number of adult residents; in the second stage, 40 persons (in five
large cities a corresponding multiple thereof) were selected at random
from the municipal registers of residents.
Targeted individuals who did not have adequate knowledge of German to
conduct the interview were treated as systematic unit non-responses.	</sampProc>
        <sampProc xml:lang="de">Personenstichprobe: Zweistufige, disproportional geschichtete
Zufallsauswahl in Westdeutschland (incl. West-Berlin) und
Ostdeutschland (incl. Ost-Berlin). In der ersten Auswahlstufe wurden
104 Gemeinden in Westdeutschland und 47 Gemeinden in Ostdeutschland mit
einer Wahrscheinlichkeit proportional zur Zahl ihrer erwachsenen
Einwohner ausgewählt, in der zweiten Auswahlstufe wurden jeweils 40
Personen (in fünf Großstädten, die mehrmals in die Stichprobe
gelangten, ein entsprechendes Vielfaches davon) aus den
Einwohnermeldekarteien zufällig gezogen. Zielpersonen mit nicht
hinreichend guten Deutschkenntnissen zählen zu den systematischen
Ausfällen. 	</sampProc>
        <deviat/>
        <collMode/>
        <sources/>
        <weight/>
        <cleanOps>C3</cleanOps>
      </dataColl>
    </method>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <restrctn xml:lang="en">A - Data and documents are released for academic research and teaching.</restrctn>
        <restrctn xml:lang="de">A - Daten und Dokumente sind für die akademische Forschung und Lehre freigegeben.</restrctn>
        <conditions xml:lang="en"/>
        <specPerm xml:lang="en"/>
      </useStmt>
      <setAvail>
        <avlStatus xml:lang="en"/>
      </setAvail>
    </dataAccs>
    <othrStdyMat/>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr>
    <fileTxt xml:lang="en"/>
  </fileDscr>
</codeBook>
